בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is כ"ה chaf hey
and we pick up with the משנה mishna on the bottom of
כ"ד עמוד ב' chaf dalet amud bet continuing to deal with keeping
neighbors, keeping things distant from one another. So let's take a look.
מרחיקין את הגורן קבוע מן העיר חמישים אמה. Merachikin et ha-goren kavua
min ha-ir chamishim ama. You keep a fixed as opposed to an
ad hoc but you have a regular threshing floor, you have to
keep that חמישים אמה chamishim ama away from the city because the
mote, what's it called, what's that called, anyway, the stuff that comes
out when you do the threshing,
flies and gets into people's face and gets into people's fields and
so on, so you have to keep that חמישים אמה chamishim ama
outside of the city. לא יעשה אדם גורן קבוע בתוך שלו Lo
ya’aseh adam goren kavua betoch shelo and therefore similarly, even if you're
in your own field and let's say you're out of the city
so you're not close to the city but you're close to your
neighbor's field, don't make it in your own field אלא אם כן
יש לו חמישים אמה לכל רוח ela im ken yesh lo chamishim
ama l'chol ruach unless you have חמישים אמה chamishim ama in all
directions so the chaff, that was the word, chaff doesn't flow, doesn't
get into your friend's field. ומרחיק מנטיעותיו של חברו ומינירו כדי שלא
יזיק Umerachik min titiotav shel chaveiro umin niro k'dei shelo yazik and
you keep it away from your friend's plantings and from your friend's
ניר, nir, ניר nir is a plowed field that's allowed to lay
fallow as a way of either destroying the weeds or as overturning
the soil, so you also have to keep it away from there
enough of a distance so it doesn't cause damage. So the obvious
question is, how is that different than the חמישים אמה chamishim ama
you said before? Is it חמישים אמה chamishim ama or is it
like a case-by-case based on the distance that it doesn't cause damage?
So that's what the גמרא gemara asks immediately. מאי שנא רישא ומאי
שנא סיפא? Mai shna reisha u'mai shna seifa? How is the beginning
different than the end? אמר אביי סיפא אתא לגורן שאינו קבוע. Amar
Abaye seifa ata l'goren she-eino kavua. No, the end is talking about
an ad hoc threshing floor. So if it's a big fixed operation
you need חמישים אמה. chamishim ama. If it's your own like little
small operation, then you sort of assess case-by-case you have to keep
it distant enough that it's not going to cause problems. היכי דמי
גורן שאינו קבוע? Heichi dami goren she-eino kavua? And what would be
this גורן שאינו קבוע, goren she-eino kavua, this non-fixed operation? What makes
it substantively different? אמר רב יוסף ברבי חנינא כל שאינו זורה ברחת.
Amar Rav Yosef b'Rebbi Chanina kol she-eino zoreh b'rachat. It's not just
a question about how regular it is, like there has to be
something that impacts the question about the distance.
So if you're not using a winnow, right, like you know, basically
you throw it all up with this big thing and it causes
the wind blows away the chaff and the wheat falls down, so
if you're doing it more I guess by hand and you're not
doing it with the same sort of size, scale of vessel then
the amount of damage that it could create or the amount that
the stuff could go at a distance is less. So you're doing
it with more small-scale types of vessels. Okay. רב אשי אמר, Rav
Ashi amar, so that's one way of reading it, that there are
two cases in the משנה. mishna. רב אשי אמר מאי טעמא קאמר.
Rav Ashi amar mai ta'ama ka'amar. No, no, no, the משנה mishna
is not saying two things, it's just explicating the reason. מאי טעמא
מרחיקין גורן קבוע מן העיר חמישים אמה? Mai ta'ama merachikin goren kavua
min ha-ir chamishim ama? Where does this idea of חמישים אמה chamishim
ama come from? What's that based on? כדי שלא יזיק k'dei shelo
yazik in order to prevent the chaff from damaging your friend's plantings.
So it's not really adding any הלכה, halacha, it's just explicating.
מתיבי. Meitivei. Now we ask, we have a ברייתא. braita. מרחיקין גורן
קבוע מן העיר חמישים אמה. Merachikin goren kavua min ha-ir chamishim ama.
You keep it חמישים אמה chamishim ama away. וכשם שמרחיקין מן העיר
חמישים אמה U'kesheim she-merachikin min ha-ir chamishim ama the same way you
keep it חמישים אמה chamishim ama away from the town, כך מרחיקין
מדלועיו ומקשואיו ומנטיעותיו ומנירו של חברו חמישים אמה. kach merachikin mi-dilu'av u-mi-kishu'av
u-mi-nitiotav u-mi-niro shel chaveiro chamishim ama. Similarly you keep it from a
place where your friend's gourds and cucumbers and plantings and tilled soil,
you keep it away from there also חמישים אמה. chamishim ama. So
so far it's like our משנה. mishna. But now the end says
כדי שלא יזיק k'dei shelo yazik in order that it should not
damage. So what in our משנה mishna appeared as you keep it
away not to damage from your friend's plantings, here in the ברייתא
braita it explicitly used those cases of מנטיעותיו nitiotav and שלא יזיק
shelo yazik and נירו niro and so on and said explicitly in
the context of חמישים אמה. chamishim ama. So that seems to be
a direct confirmation of רב אשי, Rav Ashi, that the end of
the משנה mishna is just clarifying the first case in the משנה.
mishna. So בשלמא לרב אשי ניחא, Bishlama l'Rav Ashi nicha, for רב
אשי Rav Ashi it's good. It's using the חמישים אמה chamishim ama
for this case of נירו niro and מנטיעותיו nitiotav and שלא יזיק
shelo yazik and it's all just explicating and it's all the same
הלכה. halacha. אלא לאביי קשיא, Ela l'Abaye kashya, but Abaye who reads
the משנה mishna as two separate cases, that's not reflected in the
ברייתא. braita. The ברייתא braita makes it all one case. Fine. קשיא.
Kashya. Okay, the ברייתא braita does not go according to Abaye. Now,
בשלמא מקשואיו ומדלועיו דאזיל אבקא ואתי בלבי ומצי ליה. Bishlama mi-kishu'av u-mi-dilu'av
d'azil avka v'ati b'libei u-matzi lei.
So I get the problem of keeping the need to keep it
away from your
friend's plantings and gourds and so on because the wind will come
and the dust and the chaff will be blown by the wind
and it'll land in the guy's field and מצי ליה matzi lei
is the ערוך Aruch explains it means that like it'll soak up
the nutrients,
it'll damage the things that are growing in the field. אלא מנירו
אמאי? Ela mi-niro amai? But if it's a tilled field... fallow field,
what's the problem? So big deal, so you get some chaff in
the field. What does that do? Nothing is growing there. אמר רב
אבא בר זבדא ואיתימא רב אבא בר זוטרא Amar Rav Abba bar
Zavda ve'itaima Rav Abba bar Zutra רמי rami משום דתניא mishum detanya
because you get too much chaff and it becomes, it turns into
manure. Now that's a little funny because people tend to like manure
in their fields. So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot
says אף על גב שעשאו גלל אף על גב דגלל משביח הקרקע
כשיש כולה גלל מזיק. af al gav she'aso'o galal af al gav
degalal mashbiach hakarka kesheyesh kullah galal mazik. Okay, but if all you
have is manure and you don't have anything planted there, you know,
then presumably that's not going to be good for the land. Okay.
So anyway, those are the concerns to keep the stuff, the threshing
floor with the chaff, keep it away, and once again, something that
you have to, the wind can come, cause damage, and you have
to keep it the appropriate distance away from your friend. Now let's
look at the next משנה. mishna. מרחיקין את הנבלה ואת הקברות merachikin
et hanevela ve'et hakevarot top of כ"ה עמוד א', kaf-heh amud aleph,
you keep carcasses, you've got an operation that deals with animal carcasses,
maybe you make dog food or something like that, okay? ואת ה,
ve'et ha-, it's interesting it uses נבלות, nevelot, it's not talking that
you have a slaughterhouse, okay, because the idea apparently is that the
slaughterhouse maybe you, I don't know, you know, chop it up into
meat and you move it away pretty quickly, but the, but if
you leave carcasses there for a while, I'm not exactly sure what
you're doing with them maybe, but anyway, but eventually they rot. So
you're actually having a problem here about the stench and the smell.
ואת הקברות ve'et hakevarot and how about just a cemetery? ואת הבורסקי
ve'et haburski and a tannery which deals with has a lot of
smells. מן העיר חמשים אמה, min ha'ir chamishim ama, those have to
be fifty אמה ama outside of the city. You don't want, outside
of the town, you don't want them in the town itself. So
this is like a zoning law, right? This is not even, you
know, just keeping, you know, where the people, where the people are
living, you don't want these types of things. You want the smelly
factories outside of the, you know, of the what do you call
residential area. אין עושין, Ein osin, so that's not even about one
neighbor and another neighbor, some of these things we've been seeing are
more broad zoning issues. You don't want this in the town at
all. אין עושין בורסקי אלא למזרח העיר. Ein osin burski ella lemizrach
ha'ir. Now this tannery which really smells, you only can make it
to the east. Why? Because, you know, תוספות Tosafot says the wind
apparently was, the stronger wind was from the west. I mean רש"י
Rashi says there's only a weak wind from the east. תוספות Tosafot
says it in the reverse. The strong wind is from the west.
So that'll blow it away and keep the smell away from the
city. What?
They supposedly in Israel? What?
They supposedly in Israel. Yes. Why? Is there wind going one particular
direction in Israel?
There's a constant wind from the west,
the Mediterranean,
and the
bad ones are from
the east, from Saudi Arabia. They've been causing problems for years.
The bad winds are from the east? So that's the exact opposite
of this משנה. mishna.
No, but that's unusual.
In Israel, the bad wind is from Saudi Arabia, from the east,
from the desert.
But that's an unusual pattern, right? That's when you get the sand
and everything. But it's usually from the west. Here too it comes
from the west.
The standard wind.
Yeah,
what
is, isn't there a general like, really? Yeah. What are those, what
are those called, the pattern of the way in which the wind
moves? There's a weather term for that, right? The what, maybe what?
The current?
Is it the current? Like so, isn't there like the way how
come it always takes longer to fly? It's always takes longer to
fly to Israel or from Israel? From Israel! From Israel because the
wind is always going, because the wind is always moving to the
east. It's pushing against the flight. Right. The wind patterns go from,
you know, push, you know, from west to east. Right. That's why
the planes always, they have wind resistance when they go to, to
States, and they have the wind behind them when they go to
Israel. Right. What?
Same when you're flying to California.
Oh really? Oh, it's not just about Israel. Okay. All right. So
the standard wind patterns are good. So we've established that. So okay,
there seems to be an exception going on right now in Israel,
but in general the wind patterns go from west to east. So
you want to put your tanneries in the east so that the
winds from the west blow the, blow the smoke away, blow the
stench away. אלא למזרח העיר. ella lemizrach ha'ir. רבי עקיבא אומר לכל
רוח הוא עושה חוץ ממערבה. Rabbi Akiva omer lechol ruach hu oseh
chutz mimara'ava. You can actually do it in any direction except the
west. Now the simple sense here is like he gives you more
latitude, but he says the west is going to be the worst
because there you're going to actually directly bring the, you know, the
smoke, the stench into the city. North and south he allows a
little more latitude. It doesn't have to only be in the east.
ומרחיק חמשים אמה umerachik chamishim ama and not
and you have to keep it fifty אמה ama distance. Now the
גמרא's Gemara going to exactly ask how to read רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. We'll see that in a minute. ומרחיקין את המשרה מן הירק.
umerachikin et hamishrah min hayerak. Now you keep also the, the place
where you like soak the flax which also creates a stench away
from the vegetables. ואת הכרישין מן הבצלים ve'et hakerishin min habetzalim and
the, the the leeks from the onions which apparently also can impact
the quality of the onions. ואת החרדל מן הדבורים ve'et hachardal min
hadevorim we saw. We saw that one before, the mustard seed from
from the bees, because they'll eat from the mustard and it'll affect
the honey. You keep them also similarly away, presumably also fifty אמות
amot but it doesn't say how much. ורבי יוסי מתיר בחרדל ve'Rabbi
Yosi matir bachardal ורבי יוסי ve'Rabbi Yosi allows the mustard because as
we've, excuse me, the mustard, because he can say the same way
you tell me that my mustard is impacting your honey, I'll tell
you your bees are damaging my mustard. So it's not exactly clear,
like since they're equally being damaged and damaging, no one has a
right to tell the other one to go away. You could of
course say the opposite. You could have said that each one has
the right to tell the other one to go away. It's not
that neither has. Okay, this in general gets to a broader question
of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi of whether על המזיק להרחיק או על
הניזק להרחיק, al hamazik leharcheik o al hanizak leharcheik, something that we
dealt with before.
What did you say
with the gist of this? Yeah, so here that's what I said.
Here our משנה mishnah actually does not give a distance. From the
context it sounds like the distance might be what do you call
it fifty אמות, amot, but it's not explicit here at all, and
maybe it would be a case by case based on what is
necessary given the circumstance. It is interesting that it does not give
a distance here. Okay, so now let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, they raised the question, רבי עקיבא
היכי קאמר, Rabbi Akiva heichi ka'amar, when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
any direction except the west, what is he saying? לכל רוח הוא
עושה וסומך, lechol ruach hu oseh vesomech, if you could put it
in the other direction then you can even have it within fifty
אמות, amot, very lenient. חוץ מן המערב, chutz min hama'arav, except from
the west, ומרחיק חמישים אמה, umarchik chamishim amah, the only thing, if
it's in the west it has to be fifty אמה. amah. The
other things can be even closer. ועושה. ve'oseh. Now that's a very
lenient read. It doesn't sound like that when he says any distance,
well, או דלמא, o dilma, or to read it, לכל רוח הוא
עושה ומרחיק חמישים אמה. lechol ruach hu oseh umarchik chamishim amah. No,
no, any other direction, any other of the directions, you know, you
can put it in as long as you keep it fifty אמה
amah away. חוץ מן המערב, chutz min hama'arav, except the west, שאינו
עושה כלל, she'eino oseh kelal, you can't do it at all. That
would make him closer to the תנא קמא. tanna kamma. The תנא
קמא tanna kamma says it has to be in the east and
fifty אמות, amot, and he would say it could be in three
of the directions and fifty אמות, amot, but not in the west.
Okay, so that at least is more closer position to the תנא
קמא. tanna kamma. So the גמרא gemara says שאינו עושה כלל. she'eino
oseh kelal. תא שמע, ta shema, דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא,
braita, רבי עקיבא אומר לכל רוח הוא עושה ומרחיק חמישים אמה, Rabbi
Akiva omer lechol ruach hu oseh umarchik chamishim amah, any, he put
it in any one of the directions as long as it's fifty
אמה amah away. חוץ מן המערב, chutz min hama'arav, except the west,
שאינו עושה כל עיקר, she'eino oseh kol ikar, you can't do it
at all. מפני שהיא תדירא, mipnei shehi tadira, because it is a
constant wind. It's interesting here spelled with an אלף. alef. תוספות Tosafot
has it spelled with a ה, hei, which is consistent for the
Hebrew. Anyway, so, so okay, so everybody agrees that you know, you
allowed within the direction we allow, it have to be fifty אמה
amah away, and there are some directions that we don't allow at
all. So according to the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, we only allow
it, we only allow it in the east, fifty אמה amah away.
The other directions not at all. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva allows all
three directions fifty אמה amah away, but not the west. But certainly
the problem is that the west is the most problematic because it's
going to bring the smell directly into the into the town, and
the east would be the best from that perspective. Okay, so now
the גמרא gemara wants to focus in on this phrase "not the
west because it's regular," which presumably means that the wind currents, that's
I think the word I was looking for before, the wind currents
regularly go from from west to east. So the גמרא gemara says,
אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, amar lei Rava le'Rav Nachman, מאי תדירא,
mai tadira, what does it mean that it's constant, coming from the
west?
אילימא תדירא ברוחות, eillima tadira beruchot, which is certainly the פשט, pshat,
that that's regularly the way the wind blows from west to east,
it's the most common wind, the west wind. והאמר רב חנא בר
אבא אמר רב, veha'amar Rav Chana bar Abba amar Rav, ארבע רוחות
מנשבות בכל יום, arba ruchot menashvot bechol yom,
four winds blow every day, ורוח צפונית מנשבת עם כולן, veruach tzephonit
menashevet im kullan, and the northern wind is mixed with all the
other winds. שאילמלא כן אין העולם מתקיים, she'ilmalei chen ein ha'olam mitkayem,
and if it were not for the northern wind, which is considered
to be I guess the most pleasant or, that would not, the
world could not be sustained. אפילו שעה אחת, afilu sha'ah achat, even
one moment. So you need the northern wind to be mixed with
every wind. ורוח דרומית קשה מכולן, veruach deromit kashah mikullan, and the
southern wind is the most is the harshest. ואילמלא בן נץ שמעמידה,
ve'ilmalei Ben Netz shema'amida,
if it were not for the בן נץ, Ben Netz, the son
of the hawk. Okay, this is apparently an angel, רש״י Rashi says
that's the name of the angel, that would help you know sort
of hold back this harsh southern wind, מחרבת את העולם, macharevet et
ha'olam,
then the southern wind would destroy the world. שנאמר, shenne'emar, המבינתך יאבר
נץ, hamibinatecha ya'aver netz, from your wisdom will the hawk have wings,
יפרוש כנפיו לתימן, yifros knafav leteiman,
spread out its its its wings to the south. So you have
this idea, this נץ, netz, this hawk or this angel that's spreading
out its wings against the southern wind and protecting the world from
the harsh southern wind. Notice again by the way it's a פסוק
pasuk from איוב. Iyov. I think I'm it's going to be interesting
to see given we had so much of this focus on איוב,
Iyov, how often איוב Iyov is quoted in this מסכת. masechet. I
think it's already been twice since we last since we had that
whole אגדתא. aggadata. Okay, so anyway, so according to this you see
it doesn't sound like the western wind is the most is the
most common. It sounds like the north wind is with everything. All
right, so אלא מאי תדירא, ela mai tadira, so therefore what does
it mean constant? תדירא בשכינה. tedira bishchina. It means that that's where
the divine presence is located. It has nothing to do with the
smell going into the city and the wind blowing from the west
to the east. You don't want to put your smelly tannery in
the west because the west is where the divine presence is located.
Now, why do we know that the divine presence is located in
the west? דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
because Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi said, בא ונחזיק טוב לאבותינו, bo v'nachzik
tov l'avotenu, let us come and show our appreciation, our gratitude to
our forefathers,
שהודיעונו מקום תפילה, shehodianu makom tefilla, they knew the place, they let
us, they informed us of which direction we should pray in and
which direction the divine presence is located. How did they inform us
of this? דכתיב, dichtiv, וצבא השמים לך משתחוים. utzva hashamayim lach mishtachavim.
This is a פסוק passuk in נחמיה, Nechemya, right? אנשי כנסת הגדולה,
Anshei Knesset Hagedola, if we remember from before earlier. So that's אבותינו.
avotenu. And in this פסוק passuk it says the constellations of the
heaven bow down to God. Now, how does that tell us that
the שכינה shchina is in the west? Because this includes of course
the sun and the sun rises in the east and sets in
the west. So if you think about it, right here, if look
at visually, if right, if this is the east, if this is
the east and here's the west, the sun's movement is like this.
So the sun is bowing down to the divine presence which is
in the west. You see that? The movement. Imagine the sun, right,
is so this right, if this is a person, this is an
act of bowing down. So therefore if they bow down to God,
well the sun is bowing down to the west, so the divine
presence is in the west. Yes.
How was the מקדש Mikdash oriented with respect to...
so so right, so I'm going to get to that. This is
a fascinating גמרא Gemara that completely ignores the question of location of
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash because since you raise it I'll mention
it right now. If you think about it there's two good reasons
to say the west based on the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. In
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash first of all... east to the west?
No, the west. We, we are in the eastern hemisphere but they
were in
the... I'm saying western hemisphere, right, sorry. Anyway, in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim is to the west, number
one. Number two, ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, right, they were in the
eastern hemisphere, thank you. You know, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is here,
בבל Bavel is here, right? So so if they're in בבל Bavel
they should be they should... so there's two good reasons to pray
to the west having nothing to do with this פסוק. passuk. ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael is to the west and actually in ירושלים Yerushalayim
itself and in ארץ, Eretz, right, the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim is
in the west. And it references neither of them. And this is
a fascinating גמרא Gemara because this גמרא Gemara actually you see in
general I think, right, the whole question about is תפילה כנגד קרבנות
tefilla kneged korbanot or not כנגד קרבנות, kneged korbanot, right? Is תפילה
tefilla like רחמי, rachamei, it's more
direct communication with God, it's not seen as a substitute for קרבנות,
korbanot, right? So the fact that we always דאוון daven towards the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right, always sort of orients... interesting word orient,
I'll get to that later, anyway, orients us towards the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash and almost frames, I mean you could say not necessarily
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash represents שכינה, shchina, but of course once you're
talking about the place of the מקדש Mikdash you're framing it in
a context of קרבנות. korbanot. And here the גמרא Gemara is completely
ignoring that. And I think it's a very powerful גמרא Gemara that's
putting out a model of תפילה tefilla and about God's presence post-חורבן.
churban. The irony of course is that the פסוק passuk in נחמיה
Nechemya was when they were coming and rebuilding the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash which makes it even that much more ironic. But they're living
in a post-חורבן churban reality and they're relating to the question of
God's presence and they're not thinking of it in terms of מקום
המקדש. makom hamikdash. Okay, we're not going to reference מקדש Mikdash and
therefore,
might be we pray to the west but that has nothing to
do with מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash. And therefore, you know, so that
question where is God's presence post-חורבן? churban? Is God's presence still on
הר הבית Har HaBayit or is God's presence like thinking about no,
more in the, you know, in the heavens? And in the heavens
from a perspective of where are the heavens and where is God
or whatever that's very, we're not thinking about it in terms of
the of the הר הבית Har HaBayit and we're not thinking about
our תפילות tefillot necessarily in the context of קרבנות. korbanot. So it's
a very powerful alternative model and almost by silence it ignores the
whole obvious idea that west there's two reasons to say west from
a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash orientation. Let's just hold on a minute,
okay, and let's take a look at some other points in the
גמרא Gemara and then I'll read a תוספות Tosafot that makes this
point explicitly.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מתקיף רב אחא בר יעקב,
matkif Rav Akha bar Yaakov, רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Akha bar
Yaakov asked, ודילמא כעבד שנוטל פרס מרבו וחוזר לאחוריו ומשתחוה? v'dilma ke’eved
shenoteil pras merabbo vechozer leachorav umishtachaveh? How do you know that this
movement means bowing down to the west? Maybe the שכינה shchina is
there and the sun is departing from the divine presence and walking
backwards from the divine presence, of course and bowing sort of as
you're walking backwards. It's not exactly the same imagery, yeah there, we'll
get to that in a minute. Anyway, so maybe the divine presence
is in the east. So the גמרא Gemara says okay קשיא, Kasha,
fine, we don't know exactly but it's still I think the imagery
is better to the west. רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya סבר, Savar, now
if that weren't enough that it were saying west without referencing the
מקדש Mikdash or ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, here we actually have one
that doesn't that even rejects the idea of the west. רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya סבר שכינה בכל מקום. Savar Shechinah Bechol Makom. No, the
Divine Presence is everywhere, it's not in one local, you know, not
located prior in you know in one direction. דאמר רבי אושעיא מאי
דכתיב, Deamar Rabbi Oshaya Mai Dechtiv, what's meant by the verse? אתה
הוא ה' לבדך אתה עשית את השמים ואת הארץ, Atah Hu Hashem
Levadecha Atah Asita Et Hashamayim Ve'et Ha'aretz, you God are you are
God alone, you've made the heaven and the
earth. שלוחיך לא כשלוחי בשר ודם, Sheluchecha Lo Keshluchei Basar Vadam, your
messengers are not like messengers of human beings. שלוחי בשר ודם, Shluchei
Basar Vadam, you send a messenger to go somewhere ממקום שמשתלחים לשם
מחזירים, Mimakom shemishtalchim lesham machzirim,
from the place that they are sent forth, you know, you send
your messenger to go do something from you you're in New York
you send them to to LA, they have to come back to
New York to tell you they did their job. Okay they go
back to the place they were sent from לשם מחזירים שליחותן, lesham
machzirim shelichutan,
their agency.
אבל שלוחיך, Aval Sheluchecha, those that you God send, למקום שמשתלחים משם
מחזירים שליחותן. lemakom shemishtalchim misham machzirim shelichutan.
You send them away and they inform you they don't have to
come back to inform you. They can inform you they did their
job from where they from where they were going to because you're
everywhere God they don't have to come back to you. How do
you know this? שנאמר התשלח ברקים וילכו ויאמרו לך הננו, Shene'emar Hatishlach
Berakim Veyelechu Veyomeru Lecha Hineny,
so you send forth your you
know your lightning and they go and they say to you behold
here we are. Okay. I'm sorry, הננו, hineny, period. Oh it's another
פסוק pasuk from איוב. Iyov. ויאמרו לך הננו Veyomeru lecha hineny and
they tell you here we are. יבואו ויאמרו לא נאמר, Yavo'u veyomeru
lo ne'emar, it doesn't say they come back and they inform you.
אלא וילכו ויאמרו, Ella veyelechu veyomeru, they go you know they go
what you sent them and from there they inform you that they've
done their job. Good point, it's another פסוק pasuk from איוב. Iyov.
אלא וילכו ויאמרו מלמד ששכינה בכל מקום, Ella veyelechu veyomeru melamed sheshechinah
bechol makom,
שכינה Shechinah is everywhere. You don't have to there's no one location
where God's presence is more concentrated than
in another. ואף רבי ישמעאל סבר שכינה בכל מקום, Ve'af Rabbi Yishmael
Savar Shechinah Bechol Makom, even רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael also, תנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל מנין ששכינה בכל מקום, tana devei Rabbi Yishmael minayin sheshechinah
bechol makom, how do we know it's everywhere? שנאמר הנה המלאך הדובר
בי יוצא ומלאך אחר יוצא לקראתו, Shene'emar hinei hamalach hadover bi yotzei
umalach acher yotzei likrato, the angel that was talking to me left
and another angel was coming to meet him. So if if God's
presence is in one place and all the angels are coming from
one place, so if there was another angel coming after him he
would be coming from behind, but he was coming from the opposite
direction and meeting him, that means that the angels can come from
opposite directions which means God because apparently the angels are where God
is, so the God is in all directions. Okay so אחריו לא
נאמר, acharav lo ne'emar, it doesn't say another angel came after him
to catch up with him, אלא לקראתו, ella likrato, to meet him.
מלמד ששכינה בכל מקום, Melamed sheshechinah bechol makom, God's presence is everywhere.
ואף רב ששת סבר שכינה בכל מקום, Ve'af Rav Sheshet savar shechinah
bechol makom, even רב ששת Rav Sheshet holds this. דאמר ליה רב
ששת לשמעיה, Deamar lei Rav Sheshet lishmaya, now it's very interesting because
now it has a halakhic implication. He said to his attendant, רב
ששת Rav Sheshet was blind, so he said to his attendant, לכל
רוחא אוקמן, lechol ruchah ukman, put me in any direction. Have me
stand when I have to דאוין daven שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, have
me point in any direction it doesn't really matter God's presence is
everywhere. לבר ממזרח, Levar mimizrach, just don't have me oriented towards the
east. Why? דלאו משום דלא אית ביה שכינה, Delav mishum dela it
beih shechinah, not because the שכינה Shechinah isn't in the east. שכינה
Shechinah is in the east also, I could really point in any
direction.
אלא, Ella, rather משום דמורי ביה מיני, mishum de'mori beih minei, because
that's what the heretics say you're supposed to pray to the east
and therefore I don't want to be looked like I'm following the
heretics so I'll pray to any direction other than the east. Which
raises a fascinating question of who these heretics were that have to
pray to the east.
Does does Steinsaltz or anybody suggest any answer to who these are?
I'm trying to figure it out, who would be the specific heretics
of praying to the east. Heretics often refers to the Jewish Christians
but I don't think they're specifically praying to the east.
No, does anyone people who worship the sun?
It could be them but the phrase מיני Minim would be interesting,
right? תלמידי ישו? Talmuday Yeshu? It says תלמידי ישו? Talmuday Yeshu?
No, the נצרים. Netzarim.
Yeah so מיני Minim often refers to Jewish
Christians. I'm wondering why Jewish Christians are praying to the east unless
you know that's very that's strange. I don't know. And Mecca if
we were talking about that I don't know if they would be
referred to as מיני. Minim. Anyway that would be post what?
They didn't exist then.
They didn't exist right. The Muslim if
Muhammad was what seventh century? Seventh so that's post גמרא Gemara anyway
right.
But no but isn't there in the New Testament isn't there like
the star that rose from the east? In other words the whole
messaging is the
birth of the messiah's from the east. Maybe.
I've never heard of Christians praying in a particular direction.
I don't know.
מיני. Minim. Anyway, alright, so anyway, but here you actually have, does
he say anything signs off? It's always very disappointing sometimes because he
has all this stuff, but sometimes like the really interesting historical context
something
we've had already, it just says that that's where the heretics pray.
Thank you. Thank you. Okay. I guess that רש"י Rashi was edited
out of our רש"י, Rashi, if not רש"י. Rashi. Okay, anyway, now
look at תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות Tosfos says here, לכל רוחות אוקמן lechol
ruchos ukman have me stand in any direction. So תוספות Tosfos makes
explicit this point that our גמרא Gemara is pretty much ignoring the
basic idea that you're supposed to pray towards the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, right? Because כל הני אמוראי לית להו kol hanei Amora'ei leis
lehu
all of these אמוראים Amora'im don't hold of הא דתניא בברכות, ha
de'tanya beBrachos, שחייב אדם להתפלל נגד ירושלים, shechayav adam lehispalel neged Yerushalayim,
משום דכתיב והתפללו אליך דרך ארצם. mishum dechsiv veyispallelu eilecha derech artzam.
So because and the point is you could say okay, in ארץ
Eretz in בבל Bavel west was towards ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but if you
really held the שכינה Shechinah was in the west and it had
nothing to do with the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, we would be
דאווענינג davening in the west in you know in the United States
as well, right? Because it's always about the west, it's not about
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, and some say in any direction. הא דתניא, ha
de'tanya, נגד ירושלים. neged Yerushalayim. Okay. אלא סברי כרבי ישמעאל דאמר שכינה
בכל מקום, ella savrei k'Rabbi Yishmael de'amar Shechinah bechol makom, בכל מקום
שכינה. bechol makom Shechinah. ומאן דאמר שכינה במערב סבר כרבי עקיבא דאמר
נפישי הידירה. u'man de'amar Shechinah b'ma'arav savar k'Rabbi Akiva de'amar nefishei hidira.
So either you're praying always to the west wherever you are, or
you can pray in any direction you want. Alright, the only direction
you can't pray in maybe is the east, okay, depending on this
whole מינים Minim thing. But it has nothing to do to pray
towards ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to pray towards the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash.
Okay, but how do you know the other than the last one?
You don't know that they would've applied it to the idea of
תפילה. tefillah. That's correct. That's correct. תוספות Tosfos kind of equates them.
That is correct. ר' חנינא דשמעתין דאמר כגון אתון דיתבי לציפונא דארץ
ישראל אדרימו, Rebbi Chanina de'shmaitin de'amar kegon atun deyasevu letzfona de'Eretz Yisrael
adrimu, so that at the very end of the סוגיא sugya you
will see that one says, oh, if you're living to the north
of ישראל, Israel, pray southward. סבר לה כברייתא דברכות, savar lah k'baraisa
deBrachos,
that one opinion that will come at the very end of the
סוגיא, sugya, that holds you always pray towards ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
But these other opinions hold that you don't. So I think that's
really amazing, right? That, you know, a post-חורבן Churban reality, although again
ironically quoting a פסוק pasuk in נחמיה Nechemia and basically which was
when they were rebuilding the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and saying we
no longer have to think of the divine presence as being concentrated
in one place. You know, the same way sort of תורה Torah
becomes universal access to the holy and the center of קדושה kedusha
after the חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis, in a way the שכינה Shechinah
as well. Like just think about the statement of אין להקדוש ברוך
הוא בעולמו, ein l'haKadosh Baruch Hu be'olamo, you know, מיום שחרב בית
המקדש, miyom shecharav Beis HaMikdash, אין להקדוש ברוך הוא בעולמו אלא ארבע
אמות של הלכה בלבד. ein l'haKadosh Baruch Hu be'olamo ella arba amos
shel halacha bilvad. Where is the space that God is found? The
ארבע אמות arba amos that God is found, right? It's not in
the מקום בית המקדש, Makom Beis HaMikdash, it's where תורה Torah is
being learned, right? So there's like this universal access שכינה בכל מקום,
Shechinah bechol makom, you know, of the divine presence and even the
one that says שכינה Shechinah is in the west, which does have
a greater sense of concentration, because the fear always is that if
God is everywhere God is nowhere, right? The importance of a בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash is if you have a sense of a concentrated
place of God's presence, right, it makes God's presence real. Because if
God is always equally present, then it's you know so therefore, but
even that, right, does not does not associate it with the מקדש
Mikdash and so on. So it's a really a very like different
type of a you know of an orientation.
It's really very radical in that way and it's interesting that this
גמרא, Gemara, you know, is not more discussed in terms of that
type of whole theology. Obviously not reflected in our practice because we
do דאווען daven towards the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you know, and
again so one question is where is God to be found? And
then there's the other question about how much because if you're praying
towards the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, is that just about God's presence
or does it also frame your תפילה tefillah in a type of
a context of a substitute for קרבנות, korbanos, you know, those don't
have to go hand in hand but they often do.
And also interesting what you say so many things that could be
put together in this מלכים א' פרק ח', Melachim Aleph Perek Ches,
שלמה המלך Shlomo HaMelech in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
says,
do not think that God's in the house. It's just we need
an orientation.
Yes. But talking about talking about, right, yes, but that's actually that
itself is a fascinating is a fascinating תפילה tefillah that שלמה Shlomo
makes, because talking about the relationship of God's presence versus קרבנות, korbanos,
there at שלמה Shlomo building the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, he's sacrificing
all these קרבנות, korbanos, I don't remember how much it says, hundreds
or thousands, and it says when somebody is in a faraway land,
they will pray to you through this house and all his תפילה
tefillah talks about this as a locus of divine of prayer, not
of קרבנות. korbanos. So there also raises that important question, right, about
the place of a מקום מקדש Makom Mikdash as God's presence or
and therefore prayer or or מקום מקדש Makom Mikdash as a place
for קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, but anyway, but yeah, so it's really a
very fascinating גמרא Gemara from that perspective. I can't resist telling the
joke, okay, because you have this question like, is God's presence in
the west? Is God's presence everywhere? So the teacher comes to the
class and says, where is God? So one kid says, God is
up in heaven. Another kid says, God is everywhere. Another kid... The
third kid says, God is in the bathroom. So they say, God
is what? Why are you saying God is in the bathroom? He
says, well, every morning when we're getting ready, my mom's in the
bathroom, my dad bangs on the door and says, God, are you
still in there?
Anyway, all right, moving on. All right, I'm sorry, I couldn't resist.
All right,
anyway, he told that joke in מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot when they
were doing a סוגיא sugya about the בית הכסא. Beit HaKisei.
Yeah, that too. Okay, all right. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay.
ולאו משום דלא פשט שכינה משום דמורי ביני v'lav mishum d'lo pashat
shechina mishum d'mori beini because the מינים minim say that that's the
way you're supposed to pray. And yet, I do think that the
idea, it does not mean Christians, I think the idea that it's
praying to the rising sun is probably the bigger issue, the pagans,
although again, the phrase מינים minim was strange, but I think that
the basic sense of pagans are you pray to the rising sun,
therefore you don't want to do that. That's why you don't want
to be praying to the east. רבי אבהו אמר
שכינה במערב, Rabbi Abbahu amar shechina b'ma'arav, it's in the west. דאמר
רבי אבהו מאי אזוריא, d'amar Rabbi Abbahu mai azurya,
apparently רש"י Rashi says that this is some vernacular word that refers
to the west, so he's making a little דרשה drasha on it,
אויר יה, avir ya, the breath of God. אמר רבי יהודה מאי
דכתיב, Amar Rabbi Yehuda mai d'ichtiv, what is meant by the פסוק,
pasuk, יערוף כמטר לקחי, ya'arof kamatar likchi,
that again, this is going to be sort of showing that God's
presence is from everywhere, all these winds are coming from God. So
let my let my teaching,
drip like the dew, like the rain. זו רוח מערבית, zu ruach
ma'aravit, that is the western wind, שבא מאורפו של עולם, sheba me'orfo
shel olam, that comes from the back, the עורף, oref, the back
of the neck of the world. Now here, I actually want to
take a little minute to say something about names for the directions.
Okay, קדמה kedma means east. Why does קדמה kedma mean east? Because
a normal person orients himself or herself towards the rising sun. Hence
the word orient, which means east. So the word orient means you
face towards the sun, you face towards the east. So the קדם,
kedem, your front, is east. So therefore, אחור achor is your back
is west. And there are a few places where the word אחור
achor means west. תוספות Tosafot quotes them, and we'll be תוספות Tosafot
in a minute. Similarly, your right hand, if this is east, your
right hand is what direction? South. So what's the word for south?
תימנה, teimana, like ימין. yamin. Okay, and your left hand, שמאלה, smola,
which is used more rarely, would mean north. Okay, so the עורף,
oref, so if your קדם kedem is east, your עורף oref is
the west. So it says מאורפו של עולם, me'orfo shel olam, it
comes from the west. Take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, okay,
רוח מערבית, ruach ma'aravit, this is a great little
תוספות, Tosafot, שבא מאורפו של עולם כפי' בקונטרס מאחוריו של עולם דמערב
קרי אחור, sheba me'orfo shel olam k'feirush b'kuntres me'achorav shel olam d'ma'arav
kari achor, the
back. דכתיב אחור וקדם צרתני ודרשינן בחגיגה לימים מזרח ומערב, d'ichtiv achor
v'kedem tzartani v'darshinan b'Chagiga l'yamim mizrach u'ma'arav, וקדם v'kedem means east and
אחור achor means west.
דכתיב נמי ארם מקדם ופלשתים מאחור. d'ichtiv nami Aram mikedem u'Plishtim me'achor.
So אחור achor means west. By the way, I always thought that
that's פשט pshat of a פסוק, pasuk, I haven't seen any of
the מפרשים mefarshim say it, but in דברים Devarim it says הלא
המה בעבר הירדן אחרי דרך מבוא השמש. halo heimah b'eiver hayarden acharei
derech mevo hashemesh. What's the word אחרי? acharei? So I think אחרי
acharei just means west, דרך מבוא השמש, derech mevo hashemesh, right, the
way the sun sets. So the word אחור achor means west, קדם
kedem means east.
וקרי
נמי דרום ימין ולצפון שמאל כדאמרינן בשמעתין. v'kari nami darom yamin u'l'tzafon
smol k'd'amrinan b'shmatin. Now I gave the reason because people face the
east and that's the whole word orient. He's giving the sense from
the שכינה's shechina perspective. שכינה במערב, shechina b'ma'arav, if the שכינה shechina
is in the west, ופני השכינה למזרח, u'p'nei hashechina l'mizrach, so שכינה
shechina faces towards the east, so from the שכינה's shechina perspective, ולכך
קרי מערב אחור מזרח קדם ודרום ימין וצפון שמאל. u'l'kach kari ma'arav
achor mizrach kedem v'darom yamin u'tzafon smol. Okay, and then he goes
on. But anyway, that's but that is where
one set of the directions comes from. All right, I can't resist
doing this. Okay, so one set has to do with the person
facing the rising sun. Okay, so you have קדם kedem being the
east and אחור achor or whatever being the west. And what do
we say? תימנה teimana
and being ימין yamin and שמאלה, smola, which is sometimes used but
rarely, being the north. Okay, did I do that right? Yeah. Okay,
the other way is what? It would have probably been easier if
we had done it the other way because we normally face the
other way. Okay, I have to have him looking the other way.
Okay, fine. So קדם, kedem, exactly, אחור, achor, תימנה, teimana, and שמאלה.
smola. Okay, so now, but the other way is, the other set
of names for the directions is מזרח mizrach because why?
זריחת השמש, zrichat hashemesh, right? Okay, מערב ma'arav because of right, it's
ערב, erev, right, the night. Okay, and south is דרום darom and
north is צפון. tzafon. You know why? Because the sun travels in
the day from at the height of the day it's in the
south, it goes from the east to the south and sets in
the west, so this is
דרום. Darom. It's the
highest location, it's at the height of the sky in the south
and this is צפון Tzafon because it's hidden from the north. The
sun doesn't go into the north of the hemisphere, it goes east,
south, and sets in the west. So this has to do with
the rising and setting sun, and this has to do with the
way a person is orientated. All right, that was a little lesson
for today.
That's really the etymology of דרום?
Darom?
I think so. That's fascinating. Right? Also overall if you go to
Jerusalem in the Cardo there's מזרח, Mizrach, right? Yeah. So
the orientation of the map was east, not north.
Right, east was up. East was up. Interesting, interesting.
Right. I mean it's very modern Hebrew, but you would say like
לאבד את
הצפון, Le'abed Et Hatzafon, like you
lost your orientation, how you orient your map, right,
right, right, right.
Very
great, yeah, wasn't there a בעל צפון? Ba'al Tzafon? And yeah, it's
actually north of Israel,
I
mean it's...
I know. Anyway, okay. So now it says, okay, ירוף כמטר לקחי,
Yarof Kamatar Likchi, זו רוח מערבית, Zu Ruach Maaravit, okay, שבאה מעורפו
של עולם. Sheba'ah Me'orfo Shel Olam. תזל כטל אמרתי, Tizal Katal Imrati,
let it flow like dew my speech, זו רוח צפונית, Zu Ruach
Tzafonit, this is the north,
שמזלת את הזהב, Shemazelet Et Hazahav, it makes the gold cheap. So
Rashi says this actually means that it brings famine to the world
and that everybody has to spend their money, although before the Gemara
said that the northern wind was a good one, so maybe it
means that it makes the opposite, it makes wealth and gold available
to people. וכן הוא אומר, Vechen Hu Omer, הזלים זהב מכיס. Hazalim
Zahav Mikis. Okay, so again the word זל zal associated with gold.
I don't know where they get connecting that to the idea of
north, but anyway, כשעירים עלי דשא, Kis'irim Alei Deshe, like the winds
against the grass, so זו רוח מזרחית, Zu Ruach Mizrachit, the east
wind, שמסערת את כל העולם כשעיר Shemesa'eret Et Kol Ha'olam Kis'ir that
stirs up the whole world like שעירים, se'irim, like a שעיר, se'ir,
which is a demon, and therefore that refers therefore to the east
wind. וכרביבים עלי עשב Vichrevivim Alei Esev and like the also the
rain or whatever the drops on the grass, זו רוח דרומית, Zu
Ruach Dromit, the southern wind, שהיא מעלה רביבים, Shehi Ma'alah Revivim, it
brings up the rain, ומגדלת עשבים Umegadelet Asavim and makes the grass
grow. All right, so apparently the point of those is to say
that if all the winds are coming from God, like again God
is everywhere. תני רבי אליעזר אומר, Tani Rabbi Eliezer Omer, עולם לאכסדרה
הוא דומה, Olam Le'achsahdra Hu Domeh, the world is like a portico,
like a thing which has three walls and one open wall, ורוח
צפונית אינה מסובבת, Veruach Tzafonit Einah Mesovevet, and the northern part of
it is not is not is not sealed. So basically as I've
sort of said,
right the sun,
well okay, the sun I'm going to actually do it the opposite
way because I don't know, just because,
the sun rises in the east, is at a height in the
south and goes towards the west, okay? So the question is what
happens at night? Where does the sun go? So what they basically
understood was that there was this רקיע Rakia over the earth, okay?
There was the earth, and that after the sun set in the
west, it went it went somewhere like behind the רקיע Rakia in
order to get back out and come back and come back like
that picture over there which we happened to draw for a different
purpose, okay? So anyway,
so I so let's take a look at what he says. So
he says the world is
like this אכסדרה Achsadrah and the northern side of it is not
sealed. There's an opening on the northern side of the world. וכיון
שהגיע חמה אצל קרן מערבית צפונית, Vekivan Shehigia Chama Etzel Keren Maaravit
Tzafonit,
and when the sun reaches the northwest
corner, okay, נכספת ועולה למעלה מן הרקיע. Nichsefet Veolah Lemalah Min Harakia.
It bends and it goes around the רקיע. Rakia. Now I'm not
exactly sure, I had a hard time, I couldn't find any good
pictures on this, but you know, to try to get exactly what
the Gemara's describing, why that sort of means that the southern the
northern side is not sealed, I mean it has to get out,
but anyway, somehow the sun gets out and goes back around here
and somehow that has to do with the fact that the northern
side is not closed. Let's compare this to the Rabbi Yehoshua opinion.
רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua Omer, עולם לקובה הוא דומה. Olam Lekuvah
Hu Domeh. No, it's more like a tent, it's surrounded on all
sides. ורוח צפונית מסובבת, Veruach Tzafonit Mesovevet, and actually the northern side
is enclosed. וכיון שחמה מגע לקרן מערבית צפונית, Vekivan Shechama Maga Lekeren
Maaravit Tzafonit, and when the sun gets to the north to the
northwest corner, מקפלת וחוזרת אחורי כיפה. Mekapelet Vechozeret Achorei Kippah. So that
sounds... Now it's more like a tent, it's surrounded on all sides.
ורוח צפונית מסובבת Veruach tzfinit mesovevet and actually the northern side is
enclosed. וכיון שחמה מגעת לקרן מערבית צפונית Vekeivan shechama magaat lekeren maaravit
tzfinit and when the sun gets to the north to the northwest
corner, מקפת וחוזרת לאחורי כיפה, makafet vechozeret leachorei kippah, so that sounds
like it gets here and it goes behind in the behind the
כיפה, kippah, שנאמר הולך אל דרום וסובב אל צפון. sheneemar holech el
darom vesovev el tzafon. It goes to the דרום darom and then
it's סובב sovev to the north and סובב sovev to the north
means that when it's going behind the כיפה, kippah, when it's going
in the visible sky that you can see below the כיפה, kippah,
that's הולך. holech. When it's סובב, sovev, it's getting back to where
it has to rise from and it's going behind the כיפה kippah
and at that place it's going in the north. So I don't
have like a good picture of this about what this has to
do with going in the north but anyway yes.
Isn't isn't the idea that in the first one right the sun
never ends up in the northern hemisphere? Correct. And so as a
result there it doesn't need a lid because when the sun goes
back from the west to the east it is passing back through
the southern hemisphere right? So there's no lid right you don't need
a כיפה kippah because the sun's never in the north and so
as a result there doesn't need to be a lid.
Right wait hold on give me give me that plot that that
thing in front of you I want because I'm not having a
hard time imagining. This is your כיפה kippah okay? So now the
sun is
so let's do a demonstration yes right
so the sun starts in the east and it goes like this.
Right right starts in the east and goes towards the towards the
wait which is the south make the south towards me okay?
So rises in the east and down here the south so wait
wait no no no this is the earth
all right right so
you can't see nice so
so it rises it rises in the east right comes
goes to the south and now it comes over here right and
so now the question is so what is it gonna what's it
gonna do? So according to the first opinion it flips back over
right so it stayed and it stays to the south and comes
back and then according to the other opinion no when it comes
back down it's like going towards the north and it continues back
around to
oh you're just saying the other opinion meaning you don't need the
opening for the sun to get out the question is that if
it's going in the north when it's coming back you need the
כיפה kippah to cover it so that you don't have light I
see I see okay that makes sense. So what David is saying
is
that regardless what basically
right the sun rises in the east right goes towards the south
right I mean I'm hard having a hard time drawing three dimensions
but anyway but comes towards the west and then the question is
right what is it doing? You know what because I actually had
a good picture here because from I think NASA or something that
I got the night before that I was trying to figure this
out hold on a second let me show you this actually might
make it easier.
Hold on is that helpful that diagram?
But then this is one of them is the same
as he's suggesting.
Hold on.
There was.
All right sorry
I had a good one here I should have had it out
hold on.
I can't find. Anyway what David is saying is give me one
more second.
I'm not finding it.
All right what David is saying though is is that the sun
is that when it is that okay it goes this is all
surrounded by a כיפה kippah the way it's dark at night is
the way it's the way it's dark at night is because the
sun goes behind the כיפה kippah and therefore you don't see the
sun. So the question is when it's going behind the כיפה kippah
is it reversing its path and going towards the south? So it
sort is it making like you know and if it's reversing its
path and going towards the south you don't need the כיפה kippah
on the north because the sun never goes in the north so
sunlight will never go through and it stays behind the כיפה kippah
in the south. But if at night it goes it continues in
this path and go going behind the כיפה kippah not going underneath
you know the planet going behind the כיפה kippah but if it's
going behind the כיפה kippah to the north right and then it's
coming back then you're gonna need the כיפה kippah to so you
don't get the light of the sun when it when it leaves.
What about the רקיע Rakia vs כיפה? kippah? The כיפה kippah vs
רקיע. Rakia. Yeah they they it doesn't seem like they understood that
okay. Yeah I know I mean actually the מהרש"א Maharsha says right
there's a whole debate in פסחים Pesachim whether we think it goes
underneath. This idea of going to the north might include might be
part of that idea of going underneath but I think we got
the basic idea okay? So the sun goes behind the כיפה kippah
and if it's got and if it's going behind the כיפה kippah
to the south you don't need the כיפה kippah to be covering
the earth to the north but if it's going behind the כיפה
kippah to the north then you do need it okay.
What's the difference between כיפה kippah and the רקיע?
Rakia? is the רקיע rakia basically, yeah, I think so. Yeah, yeah.
Okay, so, okay,
שנאמר she'ne'emar הולך אל דרום וסובב אל צפון. holech el darom ve'sovev
el tzafon. So you see that in the night it does go
to the north, so therefore, yes, the כיפה kipah has to cover
the north as well to keep it dark at night. הולך אל
דרום ביום וסובב אל צפון בלילה, holech el darom bayom ve'sovev el
tzafon balaylah, סובב סובב הולך הרוח. sovev sovev holech haruach. Okay, ועל
סביבותיו שב הרוח. ve'al sevivotev shav haruach. So what does that so
what's that mean? Because סובב sovev again the גמרא Gemara says means
is understanding to mean that it goes behind the כיפה. kipah. And
הולך holech means underneath the כיפה kipah that you can see it.
So it's going to explain it the following way: אלו פני מזרח
ופני
מערב. elu pnei mizrach u'pnei maarav. So it says both סובב sovev
and הולך. holech. So as far as the east and the west
are concerned, שפעמים מסבבתן ופעמים מהלכתן. she'peamim mesovevtan u'peamim mehalchtan. So because
sometimes, right, in the winter, if you think about it in the
winter, the sun basically does not, you know, goes the I really
needed a diagram here. But anyway, in winter the day is very
short. So the sun basically goes towards how to draw it?
Is
this a good way? So this is the east and this is
the west, right, so
I
don't know if I'm drawing this well or not. Something like this,
right, the path of the sun, right, how much does it is
that right? Is it something like that? Anyway, how much basically, you
know, is it going or maybe it's a little different? Maybe anyway,
how much anyway, in the summer maybe it's more like that. Anyway,
in the summer days, right, it goes very much to the east
and comes very much to the west. And in the winter days,
right, it's a very short path, right, and it goes something more
like
that. So is it going is it הולך holech to the east
and the west or is it סובב? sovev? Is most of the
east-west travel behind the כיפה kipah or is most of the east-west
travel like underneath the כיפה kipah when it's visible? So it depends.
In the summer, it's moving more eastern and western, you know, when
it's sort of you
know more of the movement the visible movement is in the east
and the west direction. And in the and in the in the
summer and in the winter, there's very little east and western movement.
I mean, I think רש״י Rashi let's look at רש״י. Rashi. I
think רש״י Rashi explains this better than I just did. So רש״י
Rashi says, פעמים מהלכתן, peamim mehalchtan, ביום ארוך של תקופת תמוז, beyom
aroch shel tkufat Tammuz, in a long day of the summer, שהיא
יוצאה בקרן צפונית מזרחית, she'hi yotza be'keren tzafonit mizrachit, the sun leaves
from the northeast, ושוקעת בקרן מערבית צפונית, ve'shoka'at be'keren maaravit tzafonit, and
sets in the in the northwest. So that's when the sun is
very much, you know, goes both directions in the
day. ופעמים סובבתן, u'peamim mesovevtan, sometimes it does it behind the כיפה,
kipah, ביום קצר שהיא יוצאה בקרן מזרחית דרומית, beyom katzar she'hi yotza
be'keren mizrachit dromit, ושוקעת בקרן מערבית דרומית, ve'shoka'at be'keren maaravit dromit, ומהלכתן
בלילה ג׳ רוחות. u'mehalchtan balaylah gimmel ruchot. So in the shorter days,
it leaves more from the southeast and sets in the in the
southwest and does not really, you know, go too much into the
well,
then naturally it would never go into the northern hemisphere.
It would never go into the northern hemisphere, right. So, okay. הוא
היה אומר. Hu hayah omer. I had a good picture for this,
but I lost it. Okay, הוא היה אומר, Hu hayah omer, he
used to say, אשם לרבי אליעזר. asam le'Rabbi Eliezer. In the end,
we come around to רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position here
about about that the north is not covered. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, why? כי
מן החדר תבוא סופה, ki min hacheder tavo sufah, זו רוח דרומית.
zu ruach dromit. וממזרים קרה, u'mimizarim karah, זו רוח צפונית. zu ruach
tzafonit. ומנשמת אל יתן קרח, u'minishmat Kel yiten kerach, this is another
פסוק pasuk from איוב, Iyov, זו רוח מערבית. zu ruach maaravit. ורחב
מים במוצק, ve'rochav mayim be'mutzak, זו רוח מזרחית. zu ruach mizrachit. Okay,
so what does that show in the end? So that shows that
because since it says that the northern wind oh, because since מזרים
mizarim comes the wind and מזרים mizarim is it says the north
wind and then so the word מזורה ופרוצה, mezorah u'frutzah, רש״י Rashi
says the word means that it is the exposed direction. So somehow
this פסוק pasuk in איוב Iyov more indicates like רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer that the north is the exposed direction. All right, let's keep
on moving. ואמר רב חסדא, Ve'amar Rav Chisda, רוח דרום מעלה רביבים
ומגדלת עשבים. ruach darom ma'ala revivim u'megadelet asavim. But wait a minute,
didn't we say that the southern wind, you know, brings back, you
know, raises the rain? So how come here we're saying that the
southern wind is what is it? מנשמת אל יתן קרח זו רוח
מערבית, mi'nishmat Kel yiten kerach zu ruach maaravit, which sounds like the
I'm sorry, where where am I? I'm sorry. No, what did we
say was the the southern wind here? Oh, מן החדר תבוא סופה
זו רוח דרומית, min hacheder tavo sufah zu ruach dromit, which sounds
like a whirlwind, which sounds like it's very harsh. But didn't we
say that the that the southern wind was a was a pleasant
wind?
So לא קשיא, lo kashya, הא דאתיא מטרא בניחותא, ha de'atya matra
be'nichuta, when it comes pleasantly it's a nice one, הא בשפיכותא, ha
be'shfichuta, when it comes in like a, you know, in a downpour
then it's very harsh. All right. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda,
מאי דכתיב, mai d'ichtiv, what's meant by the פסוק, pasuk, מצפון זהב
יאתה, mi'tzhafon zahav ye'eteh, זו רוח צפונית. zu ruach tzafonit. So we
said this before, somehow the northern wind is associated that with the
gold. שמזלת את הזהב shemazelles es hazahav that causes the gold to
flow, וכן הוא אומר v'chein hu omer הזלים זהב מכיס. hazalim zahav
mikis. All right, so that connects to an earlier, earlier we said
that as well. אמר רפרם בר פפא אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rafram
bar Pappa Amar Rav Chisda, מיום שחרב בית המקדש. miyom shechar Beis
HaMikdash. Okay, back to now we get finally after all of this
discussing God's presence without an orientation to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
now we start talking about the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. From the
day that the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed, לא הוגשמה רוח
דרומית. lo hugshama ruach dromis. The southern wind was never really as
brought the type of rain and moisture that it used to bring.
שנאמר shenemar ויגזור על ימין ורעב. vayigzor al yamin v'ra'ev. So again
ימין yamin is תימן, Teiman, is south, okay, and people will and
there'll be hunger. ויאכל על שמאלו ולא שבעו v'yochal al smolo v'lo
save'u and they ate on their left, which is the north, so
here again the right and the left is the south and the
north, and they were not sated. וכתיב uch'siv צפון וימין אתה בראתם.
tzafon v'yamin atta berasam. North and so north and you know there's
north and ימין, yamin, right, which is south, you God have created
them. So so ואמר רפרם בר פפא, v'amar Rafram bar Pappa, okay,
so I don't know how that sort of proves that. I don't
know what the second פסוק pasuk is exactly proving. Oh, the רש"י
Rashi says it's just proving that the word ימין yamin means the
south. It's the opposite of צפון. tzafon. Right, that gets back to
what we were saying before about תימן. Teiman. So you see that
now the south no longer bring brings you know no longer brings
the plenty to the world that it used to. So now we're
dealing with the post חורבן. Churban. Before we had completely ignored the
חורבן Churban and now we're dealing with the fact that post חורבן
Churban the world is not the way it used to be. ואמר
רפרם בר פפא אמר רב חסדא v'amar Rafram bar Pappa Amar Rav
Chisda מיום שחרב בית המקדש miyom shechar Beis HaMikdash אין הגשמים יורדים
מאוצר טוב. ein hageshamim yordim me'otzar tov. They no longer come from
the good storehouse of God. שנאמר shenemar יפתח השם לך את אוצרו
הטוב. yiftach Hashem lecha es otzaro hatov.
בזמן שישראל עושים רצונו של מקום, bizman sheYisrael osim retzono shel Makom,
ששרויים על אדמתם. sheshruyim al admasam. Now now that פסוק pasuk doesn't
really have anything to do with the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But
it does say, right, רש"י Rashi says the end of the פסוק
pasuk is לתת מטר ארצך. lases matar artzecha. It does have to
do with your living in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So it's a
concept of exile, not exactly exile of the חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis,
exile of the people from their land. And therefore and that's when
it's אוצרו הטוב. otzaro hatov. בזמן שישראל עושים רצונו של מקום, ישראל
שרויים על אדמתם, גשמים יורדים מאוצר טוב. bizman sheYisrael osim retzono shel
Makom, Yisrael shruyim al admasam, geshamim yordim me'otzar tov. בזמן שאין ישראל
שרויים על אדמתם, אין הגשמים יורדים מאוצר טוב. bizman she'ein Yisrael shruyim
al admasam, ein hageshamim yordim me'otzar tov. So now the time of
exile we no longer have the rain coming from the good place.
אמר רבי יצחק Amar Rabbi Yitzchak הרוצה שיחכים ידרים ושיעשיר יצפין. harotzeh
sheyachkim yadrim v'sheya'ashir yatspin. If you want to become smart, pray to
the south, and if you want to become rich, pray to the
north. וסימנך v'simancha and the way to remember it, again notice here
this whole סוגיא sugya reasserts the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And the
way to remember it is שלחן בצפון, shulchan batzafon, the table in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is in the north and the table
is bread, is sustenance, ומנורה u'menorah and the
מנורה menorah which is light, which is wisdom, is בדרום. badarom. So
now maybe you can pray in different directions but not because God
is everywhere, but I mean God is everywhere but because they represent
directions of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So still a בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash orientation. ורבי יהושע בן לוי אמר לעולם ידרים. V'Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi omer le'olam yadrim. No, no, no, you should always pray
to the south. שמתוך שמתחכים מתעשר. shemitoch shemis-chakim mis-asher. If you become
if you get wise you'll become rich. שנאמר shenemar אורך ימים בימינה
ובשמאלה עושר וכבוד. orech yamim bimina u'vismola osher v'chavod. Notice again בימינה,
bimina, ימין yamin we've now learned is south. Right, so south is
the is the מנורה, menorah, is חכמה, chochmah, ובשמאלה u'vismola which is
the north, which is the שלחן shulchan is עושר וכבוד. osher v'chavod.
והא רבי יהושע בן לוי אמר שכינה במערב? V'ha Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi amar shechina b'ma'arav? Wait a minute, how can you now say
that you should pray to the south? You've been telling us you
should pray to the
west. דמצדד אצדודי. dimztzadei itztidodei. All right, you sort of do it
at an angle, a little bit to the west and a little
bit to the south. אמר ליה רבי חנינא לרב אשי Amar lei
Rabbi Chanina l'Rabbi Ashi כגון אתון דיתבי בצפונה דארץ ישראל אדרימו אדרומי.
kegon attun d'yasvin bitzfona d'Eretz Yisrael adrimu adrumi. You are sit in
the north of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, pray to the south. ומנלן
דבבל לצפונה דארץ ישראל קיימא דכתיב מצפון תפתח הרעה על כל יושבי
הארץ. U'minalan d'Bavel litzfona d'Eretz Yisrael kayma d'ch'siv mitzafon tipasach hara'a al
kol yoshvei ha'aretz. Okay, so again fascinating גמרא. Gemara. The first part
completely ignores בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, allows you to pray in maybe
in any direction or to the west but not having nothing to
do with the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and then the end of
the סוגיא sugya reasserts wait, wait, wait, wait, there's something about the
חורבן. Churban. We're not living in the type of perfect world we're
supposed to be living in. The rains aren't coming in their time,
we're in exile and we have to be orienting ourselves towards the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you know towards that type of of
a reality. So very different theologies here. And let's just read the
last line to get to the משנה. Mishnah. מרחיקין את הפשתה מן
הירק. Marchikin es hapeshta min hayerek. You have the the flax away
from the vegetables. תנא רבי יוסי מתיר בחרדל. Tana Rabbi Yosi matirei
b'charda. We saw this before, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi allows you to
have your mustard near the bees. שיכול לומר לך עד שאתה אומר
לי הרחק חרדלך מדבורי. sheyachol lomar lecha ad she'atta omer li harcheik
chardalcha midvorai. You tell me keep my honey my mustard away from
your bees. הרחק דבורך מחרדלי, Harcheik dvoracha michardali, you keep your bees
away from my honey שבאות ואוכלות לגלגלי חרדלי. sheba'os v'ochlos ligluglei chardali.
They they come and eat the you know the flowers of my
of my mustard. So therefore you keep your bees away from my
mustard excuse me I meant. So therefore because each one. is equally
מזיק mazik and ניזק, nizak, nobody can demand either one to get
out of the way. Of course, you could say they could both
demand either one, but anyway, that's once again רבי יוסי's Rebbi Yosi
position that we've seen in different variations. Okay, we will end with
this.